so in terms of
not self
a person can get the idea
that most people have i mean a normal human
most people have i mean a normal human
being knows
they are going to die
so they they know
without reflecting that much
i'm not in control of my body fully
you know
so they get that idea that
it's not mine
you know i'm not in control
but they don't
they don't understand not self they
still take things personally they still
take the body personally yeah even
though you know
overall you're going to yeah
so why is that
i was supposed to say they haven't
really thought about it deep enough
or contemplated but and some people did
but they started infatuated with life
because of the how they act exactly yeah
so they act as though it is theirs like
you can have all the ideas you want but
if your behavior is not
mirroring those ideas
that's where you're fueling those wrong
assumptions so on one end yes when
you're you know thinking clearly you
recognize all these
characteristics of existence but then
out of habits and carelessness the body
still uh goes to its sensuality resists
uh goes to its sensuality resists
discomfort indulges in food doesn't
practice sensory strain and that's the
the cesspit of the that's the like the
the roots
where your wrong views are being fed
from so although your ideas
so although your ideas
are you know different to that
you're actually going about things it's
very much accordance to sense of control
and i'm going to live forever
so yes you need to have the right ideas
but now you need to start doing them
you need to start doing the right thing
you need to start have like you need to
purify your behaviors to mirror those
ideas because yeah it's like exactly that's
because yeah it's like exactly that's
and that's why there were summoners in
brahmins outside of the buddhist
teaching who did actually
who did actually
ponder upon like you know oh i'm no one
to nothing anywhere in the world
nobody's anything to me
like it's just like
you're basically circumstantial
that's that's your sense of control it
can end at any moment and he said that's
like the foremost of the outsiders views
and the point was that
now if you actually not just think that
view once a month
or be convinced that you're holder of
that view but okay start whenever you
want to act towards the world towards
him her or this or that
you first put that view
that you're nothing to no one anywhere
in the world and nobody's nothing it's
just oh you would not be able to engage
in passion aversion distraction
and they were then people who
made the effort
and their behavior did start to
correspond to those views and those were
the people that would have met in the
suttas who needed very little
instruction for final liberation because
they did a great amount of work already
for example if
so i might i might logically or or
reason that feelings are not mine
because they're always changing and you
know what do i feel now i feel pain now
i feel pleasure
oh yeah yeah i can see that now
you know i can
like even uh record all my feelings sure
10 o'clock it's like this what's the
time now collect the information about
it study it and i can see
definitely yes and it's
it's kind of mirrors that right view you
know paper yeah yeah yeah in theory
but well that's in the nutshell i'll be
downloading commentaries basically
it's that impersonal take almost like a
scientific collection of observational
facts of the buddhist teachings it's
always like the list and comparisons and
permutations but that's not a dhamma because again
but that's not a dhamma because again
yeah go on so i see that it's uh i i
understand in theory that
it's uh impermanent
or inaccessible to my control the
feeling but now
as i feel what do i do when i'm feeling
pain yeah
no i must i missed am i trying to get
rid of it or am i unmoved by it i must
graft that idea onto inevitably you'll
be trying to get rid of it through using
those ideas yeah yeah
but if you then really start to
understand those ideas you realize
thinking about the dhamma does not mean
that's the dhamma
so you can have all the ideas but if
you're not actually applying it rightly
there is no dhamma there
and that's important to recognize
because otherwise people can easily slip into a
otherwise people can easily slip into a
view of well as long as i think about
the dhamma i am on the path but you're
not you're on the path when you become a
sort upon that's the beginning of the
path not if you don't see the dhamma means
not if you don't see the dhamma means
you don't see the path how can you be on
the path if you don't see the path
and you will not become a sort of just
on account of such ideas you need to
actually start
applying them and enduring things on the
right level
so
i say well feelings are not mine not my
personal great thing theory
so what do you do now i'm feeling a lot
of pain or
prospective pleasure a lot of pleasure
so let's say there is a prospect of
pleasure now let me apply that
what do you do in the face of prospect
of pleasure
i don't delight in it
and what else
what else
do you act towards it
no follow it oh shouldn't do it for how
long exactly
exactly
exactly so if those are the truths that
you understood that you accepted that
you intellectually verified as correct
now you start doing it so this thing is
not mine
yeah but it's it's not in my control
it's a trap it's suffering okay
great but now they're saying but but i'm so
but now they're saying but but i'm so
say in the beginning i am faced with
feeling it this feeling is pressuring me
it's touching me
it does feel like mine
but i have the outside so you have a
note exactly but you have an option now
it feels like yours
and the option there is okay so what do
you do do you accept the pressure that
it's yours
or do you not accept it it's mine oh
yeah look this is yours i mean you know
when when the fisherman throws
a bait with the food
it's for the fish it's yours take it
yeah so that you get hooked
yeah i accept the pressure the bait
exactly well sorry i accept that there is
well sorry i accept that there is
pressure
there is a that is a bait but i don't
yeah by not taking you might not
necessarily see the bait but you can
already understand it by not acting out
of pressure
you are safe in regard to debate
you might not see it immediately but at
least you know as long as i don't take this
you know as long as i don't take this
there will be no bait i'm hooked with
and that's that's why i said it's
important to recognize that dhamma
begins with saudi party
not with the ideas of dhamma and even
the clarity you might have
because if you do
you will be creating that discrepancy
between your ideas that you're convinced
are putting you on the path of dhamma
and your behavior that it's still not
matching it
your lack of endurance your lack of
recognition of the dry level lack of
restraint in regard to need to manage
discomfort and unpleasant things
but if you don't have such view and you
reckon as yeah these ideas as clear and
as pleasing as they are
they might be very right and i might
verify later on that i was spot on right
from the start but the only way i'll do
that is not about you know through holding
is not about you know through holding
these views about the ideas and so on
and feeling saved on account of it no
it's okay now let me do that in regards
to sensuality aversion and distraction
only three things
you don't need to seek the verification
anywhere else because that's how you
yeah well that's how you verify exactly
that's how you can only
you will ever only be able to verify it
so when things pressure you can have a
view and you can agree with my view yeah
we can both agree that feelings are not
so and we can write scholarly papers on
it and dissertations and pages and pages
of references and and create a whole
network of information
that's not a dhamma that's the
information of the dharma
dhamma is when things are endured on the
right level
so i understand feelings are not
myself they don't belong to me
they don't belong to me
or they just come and go
great now when things come and go let them
now when things come and go let them
come and go without acting out of them
without trying to get rid of them
without delighting them without
welcoming them
and keep doing it for as long as it
takes and it might take forever
and it might take forever
and uh
yeah so
anyway the very the verification that
that has worked is the fact that
feelings no longer pressure
no longer pressure
well eventually yes exactly yeah of
course just even the
just even the
the pressure felt will will not be
well it will diminish there will be no
pressure in the end
that's what a contact cannot
pass the pressure contact whatever
translated cannot uh pressure the
groundless one when there is no ground
to apply that pressure for an hour ahead
so
he our hand
is unable
unable
to experience pressure
of any kind anymore
mentally
so he's beyond he cannot pressure
nothing can pressure him
because there's nothing for him anymore
well yeah yeah so that determination
of self the thing that determines
itself
is no longer there
yeah but now we're getting a bit
abstract like you know specular about it but
like you know specular about it but
no because he and you think sufficiently
on the right level
that's why nothing can pressure him
anymore because that's the difference as i said
because that's the difference as i said
many times before when pressure arises
people use even the dhamma to get rid of
the pressure not to endure it and
understand it through enduring
no to get rid of it
and that's why they're not enduring it
rightly and that's why that's not the
dharma that's why that's management versus
that's why that's management versus
uprooting you